hi everyone i'm arnell and today we're
going to look at
the causative specifically the causative
verbs
have get make and let
these look like normal verbs why are
they important
when we use these verbs in a causative
way they have a very
unique structure and a special purpose
let's take a look here's a basic concept
of causative verbs you don't do the
action
someone else does the action but you are
in control
i know this seems a little bit dramatic
but it's the basic idea
so with this idea in mind let's look at
the causative in four steps
paying for a service ask convince
persuade force and permission
we're gonna spend the most time on steps
one and two
with have and get and at the end of this
lesson
i'll have a mini test for you
number one paying for a service have
something
plus verb number three get something
plus
verb number three what do i mean by verb
number three
verb number three is the past participle
for example
play played played eat
ate eaten you can see my past participle
there
okay let's compare
i iron my shirts every week
i have my shirts ironed every week
what's the difference the first example
i do the work the second example
i pay for this service i don't do the
work
i could also say i get my shirts ironed
every week have get
is there a difference they mean the same
thing
have is just slightly more formal get is
slightly
less formal let's do another example
the wind was so strong that a tree
branch
smashed through my window
i repaired my window i had my window
repaired
i got my window repaired you can see
that structure
have get something plus verb number
three
i did the work i paid someone else to do
the work
if you're going to if we imagine
the causative as a person
it would be miss rich
i get my nails done every week
i'm having my pool clean tomorrow i get
all of my meals cooked
by my very own chef foofy and i had our
portrait painted
and you can use this structure with any
tense
present simple present continuous
past simple you can even use a modal
verb
i might have my boat repainted
okay obviously we don't only use a
causative for big
expensive services for example
what supermarket do you go to uh
i hate food shopping i just order my
groceries online
and get them delivered groceries are all
the things you can buy in a supermarket
groceries groceries hmm
what's the difference i had my groceries
delivered
i had delivered my groceries are these
the same thing
no big difference which one is causative
the first one right have something verb
three
the second example is what we call the
past perfect
tense had plus a verb three
so you can see one little change in your
word order
can make a big difference i have a video
on the past perfect
here if you want more information
let me know in the comments below the
last service
you paid for i had my eyes checked
recently
last point in part one because we are
paying for a service
we don't need to say who does the action
i get my nails done every week
done in terms of beauty done means
styled i get my nails done every week
i got my hair done last week
i'm getting my makeup done
i don't need to say buy a nail
technician i don't need to say buy a
hairdresser
buy a makeup artist it's always obvious
nobody's ever going to think
you got your nails done
by a dentist
okay part two
ask persuade convince we're still going
to use
have and get but the structure changes a
little bit
have someone verb one get someone to
get someone to verb 1.
in this case we really want to make it
clear
who does the action and in this case
we're not necessarily paying for a
service
let's do a few examples
oh my car has been making this weird
noise lately
really my brother's a mechanic i'll have
him take a look
have someone verb one
i can't get my six month old son to
sleep
he never sleeps get someone
to verb one
in this case is there a difference
between have and get
yes a little difference for
you which example feels more
difficult for the subject
when we use get someone to do something
we often have to persuade or convince
this person
have is a little bit more neutral i have
my students put their homework on my
desk
before the lesson starts
how do you get your students to listen
to you
the first one i ask my students to do
this
they do it so i don't have to the
second one how can i convince them
do you have any tricks or techniques
i'll have my lawyer give you a call he
might be able to give you some advice
i'll ask him to call you
getting my parents to agree with me is
almost impossible
i can't convince them it's very hard to
persuade them
okay so it's important to know this
difference
but yes sometimes we can use these
structures
interchangeably
[Music]
i hope everyone enjoyed my presentation
are there any questions
yeah um could i please have a printed
version of the presentation
of course i'll have sam print you a copy
i'll get sam to print you a copy
imagine sam is my assistant
in this case you can see there really
isn't any difference
so it's good to have that feeling but
sometimes they can be
interchangeable mini review have
something
verb three get something verb three
yes they mean the same thing but get is
a little bit
less formal more conversational
have someone verb one get someone to
verb one they can mean the same thing
but get has that stronger feeling of
needing to convince or persuade someone
okay let's move on to make
and lead part three
make someone verb one when we use
make someone do something we're really
thinking about
forcing someone
and yes there are different levels of
force
we have physical force
mental emotional force and then
neutral the robbers
made the security guard give them the
code
did the security guard have a choice no
the robbers made him do it
[Music]
sometimes my boss makes us work late on
fridays
do we have a choice not really but this
isn't
exactly physical force is it
stop making me laugh do i have a choice
no you're so funny i can't stop laughing
can you give me an example in the
comments below using make
my kids make me cut the crusts
off of their sandwiches
last one let we're almost done
let someone do something we're giving
someone permission
we're giving someone a choice and
remember
let is an irregular verb let
let let all the forms are the same
my professor let us use our phones
during the test
did our professor force us to use our
phones
no did we have a choice yes
if you wanted to you could use your
phone if not that's also fine
my sister lets me borrow her car
whenever i need it
does she force me to borrow her car no
do i have a choice absolutely if i need
her car
i have permission and of course in the
negative
this means no permission my landlord
won't let me have a pet in the apartment
do i have a choice
no i don't have permission i cannot have
a pet
and let isn't only about permission for
people
it can also mean to allow something to
happen
when you open a bottle of wine let it
breathe
for 30 minutes before drinking
[Music]
this allows the wine to breathe
okay let's do a mini test
number one i hmm next week
a i'm getting my wisdom teeth removed
next week
this is a common mistake or a common
problem with the causative
a lot of times students understand why
we need this grammar when we use this
grammar
but oftentimes they don't quite get the
structure right
so we can't change the word order and we
can't use a different form of the verb
by the way wisdom teeth are those big
teeth
at the back of your mouth that you get
when you're an adult and you do need to
remove them
sometimes number two
a new washing machine
see i had my landlord buy a new washing
machine
once again a and b don't work because
they're not the correct structure
last one number three my boss hmm
while i work
b lets me my boss lets me listen to
music while i work
technically a and c are correct
but they are not really natural right a
my boss makes me listen to music why
would your boss force you to listen to
music
my boss gets me to listen to music
again why would your boss need to
convince you to do that
you either want to or you don't
okay wonderful so
i hope today's lesson was helpful i hope
the difference between
have get let and make i hope the
differences are clear
you know what your comments always make
me smile
so leave me one down below i can't wait
to see you soon
thank you bye